<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2053">
 <fileDesc>
     <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from Emma Duffin to her sister Celia Duffin, 29 December 1915</title>
        <author>Emma Duffin</author>
        <editor>Susan Schreibman</editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
         <p>TO ADD: Letters of 1916: creating history [...]</p><!--to add-->
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
            <address>
                <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                <placeName>
                    <country>IRE</country>
                    <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                </placeName>
            </address>
        </publisher>
        <idno n="L1916_2053"/>
        <availability status="restricted">
            <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced,
                 distributed, or transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other electronic
                 or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests, write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
            <p>All rights reserved. 2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
             <!-- ADD THE FOLLOWING OPTIONAL FORMULA FOR ORPHAN WORKS<p>All rights reserved. The rightsholder could not be traced.</p>-->
         </availability>
         <date when="2015">2015</date>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
         <!--to add: -->
         <p>PUT A STATEMENT, e.g. Machine-readable transcriptions of letters from the Letters of 1916 collection</p>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
        <note type="summary">
            <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            <p>Emma (1883 - 1979) was born in Belfast and educated at Cheltenham Ladies College. She served initially in Egypt and was transferred to northern France just before the Battle of Somme,where she remained to the Armistice in 1918. </p>
            <p>Emma thanks her sister for a book of poetry sent to her, most probably a Christmas present. She describes her day-to-day work as a VAD, including interactions with the patients and the enjoyable weather. At the time of writing she had worked for 13 weeks without a day off.</p>
        </note>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
                <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                <collection type='public'>Duffin Papers</collection><!--MANDATORY -->
                <idno>D2109/9/4/C</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
    <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="receiving">
        <persName>Celia Duffin</persName>  
<!-- <date>WE DON'T HAVE A DEVOTED FIELD!!!</date> -->
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="sending"> 
            <persName>Emma Duffin</persName> 
            <date when="1915-12-29">29 December 1915</date>
        </correspAction>
    </correspDesc>
    <textClass>
        <keywords>
            <list>
                <item n="gender">Female</item>    
                <item n="tag">World War 1: 1914-1918</item>       
            </list>
        </keywords>
    </textClass>
    <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
    </langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
    <samplingDecl>
            <!--to add: -->
        <ab>to ADD: e.g. This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project Letters of 1916: creating history.</ab>
    </samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- <facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter">
        <body> 
            <div n="1" type="page" facs="#L1916_2053.0_img_1" xml:id="L1916_2053.1"><!-- or loop.index? -->
                   <opener>
                       <address>
                           <addrLine>15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Gen. Alex.</addrLine>
                       </address> 
                       <dateline>
                           <date>Dec.29/15.</date>
                       </dateline>
                       <salute>My dear old Celia</salute>
                   </opener>
                   <p>Ever so many thanks for the two little<lb/> 
                       books, they are really a joy for I have not read a line of<lb/> 
                       poetry since I left &amp; I have found several old friends in them.<lb/> 
                       I suppose your Xmas was very much like mine, very busy<lb/> 
                       with decorations, plans etc. for the men. I made my tent<lb/> 
                       quite pretty with strings of <unclear>keys</unclear>, paper lampshades, &amp; big bowls of<lb/>
                       roses (which I'm sure you didn't have!) etc. and we had a<lb/> 
                       little wee Xmas tree in the centre of the table. &#x2014; How funny<lb/> 
                       you having a man out of the tents. What was his name!<lb/></p>
                    <p>I have had some very nice Australian patients, a bit obstreperous<lb/>
                        sometimes, as you say, but jolly &amp; full of life! I am sorry<lb/>
                        for you on night duty. I simply loathed it &amp; I'm afraid my<lb/>
                        turn will be round again soon. I gather that you mean to sign<lb/> 
                        on again, is there no chance of a few days leave between. We<lb/> 
                        have no B.P. work at all, the orderlies do all that, I occasionally<lb/>
                        give one if there is a bad case &amp; no <sic>orderlie</sic> at hand but we<lb/>
                        are not supposed to &amp; we never empty them. I had a<lb/> 
                        patient to wash the other day, an <unclear>??</unclear> who had come straight<lb/> 
                        from the French trenches &amp; had never had a bath, he had felt<lb/> 
                        ill on leaving &amp; had got ill on the transport &amp; of course no nurse<lb/>
                        to look after him poor fellow. At present I have a <lb/> 
                        Pneumonia case who had a T. of 105.4 the other night, but<lb/> 
                        he is a lot better today. I have just come up from</p><pb/>
           </div> 
            <div n="2" type="page" facs="#L1916_2053.0_img_2" xml:id="L1916_2053.2"><!-- or loop.index? -->
                 <p>2</p><!-- put fw? -->
                <p>seeing <unclear>Alice</unclear> Russell off on a hospital ship, poor thing her father<lb/>
                    is dying. Matron let me off to see her on board which was<lb/> 
                    very decent of her. I shall miss her dreadfully as we have<lb/> 
                    shared a room ever since we arrived.</p>
                <p>I do like to work here much better than I expected, &amp; of course<lb/> 
                the weather is lovely &amp; I never get tired of <unclear>watching the sights</unclear>,<lb/> 
                but I do wish I could have a little more free time. I have<lb/> 
                never had a day off yet, &amp; I have been here over 13 weeks now.<lb/> 
                I wish you could come out, but of course our times would overlap,<lb/> 
                whether I shall sign on again I don't know the worst of it<lb/> 
                would be the dreadful heat in summer. Still you'd feel rather a <lb/> 
                <unclear>freak</unclear> going home when others have to stick it out, besides the<lb/> 
                climate agrees with me &amp; it doesn't suit some people at all.<lb/> 
                I must leave it till nearer the time. It made me feel a<lb/> 
                bit homesick to see Celine going home.</p>
                <p>I owe so many Xmas letters, you must excuse a short one.<lb/>
                    Best love dear, how I wonder when we'll next meet!</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Ever Yours<lb/></salute>
                    <signed><hi rend="underline">Emma.</hi></signed>
                </closer>
           </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>


    