<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2110">
 <fileDesc>
     <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from General Sir John Grenfell Maxwell to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer, 12 May 1916</title>
        <author>John Grenfell Maxwell</author>
        <editor>Susan Schreibman</editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
         <p>TO ADD: Letters of 1916: creating history [...]</p><!--to add-->
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
            <address>
                <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                <placeName>
                    <country>IRE</country>
                    <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                </placeName>
            </address>
        </publisher>
        <idno n="L1916_2110"/>
        <availability status="restricted">
            <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced,
                 distributed, or transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other electronic
                 or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests, write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
            <p>All rights reserved. 2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
             <!-- ADD THE FOLLOWING OPTIONAL FORMULA FOR ORPHAN WORKS<p>All rights reserved. The rightsholder could not be traced.</p>-->
         </availability>
         <date when="2015">2015</date>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
         <!--to add: -->
         <p>PUT A STATEMENT, e.g. Machine-readable transcriptions of letters from the Letters of 1916 collection</p>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
        <note type="summary">
            <p>This letter was written by Sir John Grenfell Maxwell (1859-1929) to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 to his death. </p>
            <p>Maxwell had been appointed commander-in-chief of the British forces in Ireland during the Easter Rising and was responsible for the suppression of the Rising. In this letter Maxwell urges O&#39;Dwyer to prevent priests from &#39;mixing up in organisations that are a danger to the realm.&#39; This letter refers specifically to the activities of Fr Michael Hayes (1873 - 1934) and Fr Thomas Wall (1877 - 1956). </p>
            <p>Bishop O&#39;Dwyer would later become renown for his letter to Maxwell on 30 May in which he denounced the shooting of the insurgency leaders of Easter Week 1916 ‘in cold blood’ and the deporting of thousands without trial, and declared Maxwell&#39;s regime ‘one of the worst and blackest chapters in the history of the misgovernment of this country’</p>
        </note>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
                <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                <collection type='public'></collection><!--MANDATORY -->
                <idno>LDA/BI/ET/239/1/3</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
    <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="receiving">
        <persName>Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
        <placeName>Limerick, Ireland</placeName>  
<!-- <date>WE DON'T HAVE A DEVOTED FIELD!!!</date> -->
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="sending"> 
            <persName>John Grenfell Maxwell</persName> 
            <placeName>Irish Command Headquarters, Parkgate, Dublin, Ireland</placeName> 
            <date when="1916-05-12">12 May 1916</date>
        </correspAction>
    </correspDesc>
    <textClass>
        <keywords>
            <list>
                <item n="gender">Male</item>    
                <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
                <item n="tag">Irish question</item>       
            </list>
        </keywords>
    </textClass>
    <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
    </langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
    <samplingDecl>
            <!--to add: -->
        <ab>to ADD: e.g. This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project Letters of 1916: creating history.</ab>
    </samplingDecl>
</encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- <facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter">
        <body> 
            <div n="1" type="page" facs="#L1916_2110.0_img_1" xml:id="L1916_2110.1"><!-- or loop.index? -->
                 <opener>
                     <address>
                         <addrLine>Headquarters, Irish Command,</addrLine>
                         <addrLine>Parkgate, Dublin.</addrLine>
                     </address>
                    <dateline>
                        <date>12th: May, 1916.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dear Lord Bishop,</salute>
                 </opener>
<p>I beg to acknowledge the letter of May 9th.<lb/> 
    from Your Lordship's Secretary. Father Thomas Wall has<lb/> 
    been reported as on 14th November, 1915, speaking in<lb/> 
    his Church at DrumCollogher against conscription. He<lb/> 
    is said to have attended a lecture by P.H. Pearse on the<lb/> 
    "Irish Volunteers of '82," and of blessing the Colours<lb/>  
    of the Irish Volunteers at DrumCollogher on 2nd:January,<lb/> 
    1916, also speaking at a meeting that took place at<lb/> 
    Newcastle West on the 17th: March, 1916.</p>
<p>Father M. Hayes is said to have been active<lb/> 
    with a certain E. Blythe organizing Irish Volunteers.<lb/> 
    In November 1915 he got printed a large number of leaflets<lb/> 
    appealing to young men of the Gaelic Athletic Association<lb/> 
    to join the Irish Volunteers. He is said to be President<lb/> 
    of the Irish Volunteer Branches at Killoughteen and<lb/> 
    Newcastle West. He is said to have been present at the<lb/> 
    Irish Volunteer meeting at Newcastle West when a certain<lb/> 
    John MacDermott delivered inflamatory and seditious<lb/> 
    speeches on 17th March, 1916.</p>
<p>When I wrote to Your Lordship on the 6th.,<lb/> 
    I hoped that you would have been able to take steps to<lb/> 
    prevent priests from mixing up in organizations that are<lb/> 
    a danger to the Realm.</p>

<closer>
    <address>
        <addrLine>The Most Rev: Edward T. O'Dwyer, D.D.</addrLine>
        <addrLine>Bishop of Limerick.</addrLine>
</address>
</closer><pb/>
            </div> 
            <div n="2" type="page" facs="#L1916_2110.0_img_2" xml:id="L1916_2110.2"><!-- or loop.index? -->
                   <p>If these reports be true, <del>and</del> it should not be<lb/> 
                       necessary for me to make definite charges supported by<lb/> 
                       evidence against these priests whom I imagine will not <lb/>
                       deny their participation in the Irish Volunteers movement<lb/> 
                       which has led to such deplorable events all over Ireland.<lb/> 
                       Therefore it should not be difficult for your Lordship, <lb/>
                       under such disciplinary power as you may possess, to<lb/> 
                       prevent at any rate priests from mixing up with and inciting<lb/> 
                       their flock to join an organization such as the Irish<lb/> 
                       Volunteers have proved themselves to be.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I beg to remain,<lb/>
                        My Dear Lord Bishop,<lb/>
                        Yours very truly,</salute>
                    <signed>J. G. Maxwell</signed>
                </closer>

           </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>


    